# Peterson Jr. Yuhala

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · TRUSTED COMPUTING

IIUN, Neuchâtel, Switzerland



Yaounde, Cameroon

Sept. 2013 - Sept. 2018

Sept. 2011 - June 2013

Sept. 2006 - June 2011

April 2024 - Present

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

April. 2019 - March 2024

April. 2019 - Present

📕 (+41) 79 683 95 57 | 🗷 peterson.yuhala@unine.ch | 💣 yuhala.github.io | 🖸 github.com/Yuhala | 😾 gitlab.com/Yuhala | 🗖 peterson.yuhala-14009411a

"Be the change you wish to see in the world."

## About

I am a postdoctoral researcher in the Institue of Computer Science at the University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland. I conduct research in the field of systems security, with particular attention on trusted execution environments (TEEs). I obtained my PhD entitled "Enhancing Security and Performance in Trusted Execution Environments" at the University of Neuchâtel in April 2024.

## **Education**

**University of Neuchâtel** Neuchâtel, Switzerland

PhD in Computer Science

April 2019 - March 2024 • Thesis: Enhancing security and performance in trusted execution environments

- Advisors: Pascal Felber, Alain Tchana, Valerio Schiavoni
- National Advanced School of Engineering (ENSP)

Masters of Engineering in Computer Science

- · Thesis: Memory address translation optimization in virtualized systems
- · Advisor: Alain Tchana

**Sacred Heart College** Bamenda, Cameroon

GCE Advanced Level

25/25 points (perfect score)

**Sacred Heart College** Bamenda, Cameroon

GCE Ordinary Level

• 33/33 points (perfect score)

## **Research and Work Experience**

Postdoctoral researcher Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Computer Science Institute - UniNE

Efficient privacy preserving computation with TEEs and homomorphic encryption

**Research Assistant/PhD Candidate** 

Computer Science Institute - UniNE • Efficient confidential computing with TEEs.

· Adding TEE support in GraalVM CE for sensitive data protection in the cloud (collaboration with Oracle labs Zürich)

• Enhancing IoT security and privacy with TEEs and machine learning (VEDLIoT project)

**Teaching Assistant** Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Faculty of Science - UniNE

· Networking and Web Technologies

Discrete Mathematics for Computer Science

Computer programming for biologists (Python, R, Linux)

Research Intern Toulouse, France March. 2018 - Sept. 2018

Toulouse Institute of Computer Science Research (IRIT)

• Memory address translation optimization in virtualization systems

**Engineering Intern** Douala, Cameroon

Les Brasseries du Cameroun July. 2017 - Sept. 2017

· Setting up a sales management module based on Odoo ERP for wholesalers in the brewery industry

PETERSON JR. YUHALA · RESUME JUNE 13, 2024

Intern Yaounde, Cameroon

National Advanced School of Engineering

- Leveraging microcontrollers to build domotic systems
- Implemented prototypes for home automation based on several microcontroller platforms: Arduino, MSP-430, ESP32
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/arduino-projects
- · Building programmable digital circuits with Altera FPGA

# **Projects**

## Securing IoT data with Arm TrustZone and ML.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel (VEDLIoT project)

Feb. 2023 - Present

July. 2016 - Sept. 2016

- Porting hardware peripheral device drivers to OP-TEE OS
- · Leveraging machine learning classification techniques to filter out sensitive data from data streams

#### Multilanguage program partitioning for TEEs.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel (collaboration with Oracle labs Zürich)

Sept. 2021 - Dec 2022

- Developing a programming language implementation with Oracle's Truffle framework which provides generic AST nodes to encapsulate sensitive data (i.e secure values) in polyglot applications
- Developing a generic taint analysis tool to analyse the resulting ASTs to deduce sensitive program portions
  which are partitioned into Intel SGX enclaves
- See: https://gitlab.com/Yuhala/generic-tools

## Making Intel SGX switchless calls configless

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel

Aug. 2021 - Feb. 2022

- Identifying limitations of the static configuration policy in Intel SGX's switchless call library
- Building a dynamic SGX switchless call system which obviates the performance penalty due to static configurations
- See: https://gitlab.com/Yuhala/zc-switchless

#### **Partitioning Java programs for TEEs**

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel (collaboration with Oracle labs Zürich)

July 2020 - June 2021

- Developing a tool to partition Java-based applications for Intel SGX enclaves
- The program-partitioning technique leverages Java annotations and byte-code transformations to partition Java classes into trusted and untrusted components
- The partitioned components are ahead-of-time compiled with GraalVM into native executables that run in and out of secure enclaves in a distributed fashion
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/montsalvat

#### Secure and persistent machine learning model training.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel

April 2019 - June 2020

- Leveraging persistent memory (PM) to provide efficient fault-tolerance guarantees for applications running in TEEs like Intel SGX
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/plinius

#### Memory address translation optimization in virtualization systems.

Toulouse, France

Institut de Recherche en Informatique de Toulouse (IRIT)

March. 2018 - Sept. 2018

- Modifying the Xen hypervisor to provide contiguous memory to paravirtual guest VMs
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/xen
- · Building a VM placement simulator.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/placement-simulator

### SIMbox fraud detection.

Yaounde, Cameroon

Sept. 2017 - Jan. 2018

National Advanced School of Engineering

- Developing a tool for SIMbox fraud detection based on the ELK stack
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/elk-fraud-detection

# **Publications**

#### **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

Fortress: Securing IoT Peripherals with Trusted Execution Environments

Peterson Yuhala, Jämes Ménétrey, Pascal Felber, Marcelo Pasin, Valerio Schiavoni

. SAC 2024 (2024). Association for Computing Machinery, 2024

A Holistic Approach for Trustworthy Distributed Systems with WebAssembly and TEEs

Jämes Ménétrey, Aeneas Grüter, Peterson Yuhala, Julius Oeftiger, Pascal Felber, Marcelo Pasin, Valerio Schiavoni CORR abs/2312.00702 (2023). 2023

SecV: Secure Code Partitioning via Multi-Language Secure Values

JUNE 13, 2024 PETERSON JR. YUHALA · RESUME

#### Peterson Yuhala, Pascal Felber, Hugo Guiroux, Jean-Pierre Lozi, Alain Tchana, Valerio Schiavoni, Gaël Thomas

Proceedings of the 24th International Middleware Conference, 2023, Bologna, Italy

#### SGX Switchless Calls Made Configless

Peterson Yuhala, Michael Paper, Timothée Zerbib, Pascal Felber, Valerio Schiavoni, Alain Tchana

2023 53rd Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN), 2023

(No)Compromis: Paging Virtualization is Not a Fatality

Boris Teabe, Peterson Yuhala, Alain Tchana, Fabien Hermenier, Daniel Hagimont, Gilles Muller

International Conference on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE), 2021, Virtual, USA

Plinius: Secure and Persistent Machine Learning Model Training

Peterson Yuhala, Pascal Felber, Valerio Schiavoni, Alain Tchana

2021 51st Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN), 2021

Montsalvat: Intel SGX Shielding for GraalVM Native Images

Peterson Yuhala, Jämes Ménétrey, Pascal Felber, Valerio Schiavoni, Alain Tchana, Gaël Thomas, Hugo Guiroux, Jean-Pierre Lozi

Proceedings of the 22nd International Middleware Conference, 2021, Québec city, Canada

Talks.

SecV: secure code partitioning using multi-language secure values

Bologna, Italy

24th ACM/IFIP International Middleware Conference

Dec. 2023

June 2023

June 2023

**SGX Switchless Calls Made Configless** 

Porto, Portugal

53rd International conference on Dependable systems and Networks

**Enhancing IoT Security and Privacy with TEEs and Machine Learning** 

Porto, Portugal

53rd International conference on Dependable systems and Networks (Doctoral Forum)

**Partitioning Java Programs for Intel SGX** 

Zürich, Switzerland

Huawei Research Center Zürich

Dec. 2022

SecureL: Secure code partitioning via multi-language secure types

Rennes, France April. 2022

Dec. 2021

Dec. 2021

EuroSys Doctoral Workshop 2022

**Montsalvat: Intel SGX shielding for GraalVM Native Images** 

Virtual Event, Québec, Canada

22nd ACM/IFIP International Middleware Conference

Secure and Efficient Learning: approaches, techniques and threats

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Conférence Universitaire de Suisse Occidentale (CUSO)

Secure and persistent ML model training with persistent memory and Intel SGX. 51st International conference on Dependable systems and Networks

Virtual Event, Taipei, Taiwan

June. 2021

Paging virtualization is not a fatality.

Biarritz, France

Conférence francophone d'informatique en Parallélisme, Architecture et Système (COMPAS)

July. 2019

## **Honors & Awards**

#### **DOMESTIC**

2018	Salutatorian, Computer Engineering class of 2018, ENSP Yaounde	Yaounde,
		Cameroon
2013	Valedictorian, Class of 2013, Sacred Heart College	Bamenda,
		Cameroon
2013	Ralph C. Okwen Award , Overall best high school science student, Sacred Heart College	Bamenda,
		Cameroon
2013	<b>2nd Award</b> , Academic Excellence Award for a perfect score at the Cameroon GCE A-Level 2013 session (25/25	Cameroon
	points)	
2011	<b>1st Award</b> , Academic Excellence Award for a perfect score at the Cameroon GCE O-Level 2011 session (33/33	Cameroon
	points)	

## Academic service

## **Scientific volunteering**

University of Neuchâtel

- $\bullet \ \, {\tt Organizing \, a \, STEM \, bootcamp: } \\ \textbf{https://scienceprojectscmr.github.io/}$
- Writing scientific articles for LexTech institute blog: https://www.lextechinstitute.ch/blog
- University media presence: secure data processing in the cloud

#### **Scientific peer reviewing**

University of Neuchâtel

- Artifact Evaluation Committee ASPLOS 2024
- Artifact Evaluation Committee OSDI 2021
- Artifact Evaluation Committee EuroSys 2021
- Sub-reviewer IC2E21

#### **Conference volunteering**

University of Neuchâtel

- Student Volunteer OPODIS 2019
- Student Volunteer COMPAS 2018

## Skills

**Programming Languages** C/C++, Java, Python

**Systems Security** Intel SGX, ARM TrustZone, OP-TEE

Web Development HTML5/CSS, JavaScript, SQL, Laravel with PHP, Flask

**Miscellaneous** Linux, Git, Shell(Bash), Docker, LaTeX

## Languages\_

English Native proficiencyFrench Native proficiency

## Interests\_

**Reading** I love books on politics, economics, and personal development.

**Sports** Football, Biking **Music** Piano, Singing

**Board games** Chess

# **References**

## **Pascal Felber**

 Professor pascal.felber@unine.ch University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland

## **Alain Tchana**

 Professor alain.tchana@ens-lyon.fr ENS Lyon, France

## Valerio Schiavoni

 Assistant Lecturer valerio.schiavoni@unine.ch University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland